<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The proselyte of Rome called back to the communion of the Church of England in a private letter thought very fit and seasonable to be made publick.</title>
            <author>L. W.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67555</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W81</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24582</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08251206</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08251206</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41190</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67555)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41190)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1243:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The proselyte of Rome called back to the communion of the Church of England in a private letter thought very fit and seasonable to be made publick.</title>
                  <author>L. W.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Clavell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: L.W.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:41190:1"/>
            <p>Licenſed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 19. 78.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. JANE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41190:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Proſelyte of Rome CALL'D BACK TO THE COMMUNION OF THE Church of England.</p>
            <p>IN A PRIVATE LETTER, THOUGHT Very fit and ſeaſonable to be made Publick.</p>
            <p>To the ROMANS.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Cap. XI. v. 20.22.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Be not high minded, but fear: Otherwiſe, Thou alſo ſhalt be cut off.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Apoc. II. 5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Remember therefore from whence thou art fallen, and repent, and do thy firſt works.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Clavell</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:41190:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41190:2"/>
            <head>To the Reverend and Learned Author.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SInce I had the honour and ſatisfaction of ſeeing your Papers, I have blamed your delay in the publication of them; eſpecially being deſigned to recall a <hi>Romiſh Proſelyte</hi> that was gone from the Communion of our Church, they might (in this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy and diſtracted Juncture) have ſeaſonably help'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the recovery of others, whoſe temporal as well as eternal Intereſts make them as eager and deſirous of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction. I know that Modeſty is a vertue, and Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a very commendable thing: but Charity and Love to the Souls of men is much more ſo. You have lived to ſee the Church forlorn and deſolate, perſecuted and ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly forſaken; and after a little reſpite and the hopes of ſettlement, to be again threatned and menac'd with a final overthrow.<note place="margin">Pſal. 137.7.</note> 
               <hi>Down with it, down with it even to the ground,</hi> cry our Modern <hi>Edomites.</hi> And when the Church did need the Aids of thoſe who loved her, we know ſhe found your Zeal, and Reſolution and Courage in her ſervice: And that now you ſhould flag when you are ſo well arm'd and prepar'd for Combat, or be backward when her Adverſaries are pecking at the very foundations with Axes and Hammers, and striving to undermine her by Artifice or Violence; And you a Champion ſo try'd and experienc'd, and furniſh'd to defend her; I cannot imagine, unleſs you
<pb facs="tcp:41190:3"/>are more tender than formerly, and fear taking of harm by being expoſed to the open Air. I think I have heard that the time has been,<note place="margin">Neh. 4.1.</note> when, like <hi>Nehemiah</hi>'s Builders, you wrought with one hand in the Churches ſervice, and with the other you hold a weapon for her defence and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour. You know the Arguments that mov'd you then; and what hinders but they ſhould now prevail? I am, you ſee, warm in the Churches cauſe, nor do I believe that you are leſs concern'd. But if I ſeem to reproach or lament your remiſsneſs in theſe ſeaſonable Circumſtances to ſend abroad your uſeful preparations, let me not be thought rude or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannerly, becauſe I hereby not only vindicate you from the common fault of being forward to print, but likewiſe ſhew the high value I have for your Perſon and Papers, and that I believe them to he very uſeful for the Publick benefit.</p>
            <p>As to the Gentleman you deſign to reduce, I only know him upon this occaſion, and therefore can ſay little of his Learning or Ingenuity, or the Motives that made him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from us: But if after all your endeavours to convict him he ſtill remains hard and untractable, and <hi>refuſeth to hear the voice of the charmer, charm he never ſo wiſely,</hi> he muſt be let alone in the obſtinacy of the <hi>deaf Adder,</hi> and to our Prayers to ſoften him, when your Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments cannot alter him; but when the World have ſeen your Papers, and know that he has done ſo; They'l ſtrain their Charity to ſuſpect, that ſomething elſe beſides the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb facs="tcp:41190:3"/>advantage of <hi>Infallibility</hi> perſwaded him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt; and till he can anſwer your Arguments, they'l be apt to think, that the exchange of Opinion was not for Faith but Fancy, and that while he dreamed that he left uncertainty, it was to be ſecure of nothing.</p>
            <p>But if you ſhould have that Friendly influence upon him by your pains and endeavours to call him back, hee'l (by that Charity that is more Catholick than the Religion he leaves) be glad, that by his fall ſo great an advantage has been offer'd to the world, and that others may be reduc'd thereby to the ſober enquiry upon what bottom they truſt their Salvation, and ſee upon what ſlender and fickle grounds their Faith has been fixed; And what thoſe Grounds are, all men will ſee when they peruſe your Tractate. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, we have reaſon to thank ſuch men as you for aſſerting the Churches cauſe in theſe Controverſies; For who now that is moſt freakiſh in folly and Enthuſiaſm, has a front to ſay, That the Sons of our Church are warp'd from what is Primitive and truly Orthodox; or Factors for the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Intereſt; or wiſh well to the promoting that Cauſe amongſt us, &amp;c Let us hear no more ſuch outcries againſt the Church of <hi>England,</hi> nor againſt thoſe who are exact and punctual in the decent performance of Gods publick Worſhip, and the circumſtances of Order and Diſcipline. For the gaudy Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions of <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> are more contemned by ſuch men, than the looſer and more careleſs dreſs of <hi>Amſterdam</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:41190:4"/>and <hi>Geneva.</hi> And you amongſt many others have freed our Church from this whining &amp; unjuſt imputation, in that you have not only ſhaken, but everted that fundamental Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, upon the fall of which all the ſuperſtructure tumbles.</p>
            <p>As to your Quotations, they are ſo proper and peculiarly adapted to every period, that you had very great luck to happen on the choice of them. And for the Tranſlations which your Charity ſuffer'd to be made of them, for the uſe of your meaner and more unlearned Reader; they, I perceive, were done by one whoſe skill in Grammar did exceed his ſenſe in Theologie and Divine Controverſies, which may excuſe them to the Criticks and men of brisker fancy. However, Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlating is a very tedious task, and ſo long as they are true and literal, they are juſtifiable enough againſt the keeneſt and moſt ſnarling Cenſurers.</p>
            <p>I am loth the Meſſenger ſhould ſtay, and therefore only wiſh your Reader may be impartial and conſiderative, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prejudic'd and ſerious, and that your Papers may convince and confirm him, that they may have their deſign on the Gentleman you'd recall, and advance the intereſt of Truth and Goodneſs amongſt all men; that they may help to allay that bitterneſs, and heal thoſe Animoſities and wild Conceits that trouble the Chriſtian World, and that all that ſee them may endeavour after the <hi>things that make for Peace.</hi> Which is the Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your faithful Servant.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Dec. 2. 1678.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41190:4"/>
            <head>THE RELIGION OF THE Church of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <head type="sub">IN A PRIVATE LETTER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SInce I have known you ſo long, I am ſorry I knew you no better. I aſſure you I intended to treat you as an entire Friend, but you wreſt my words to a harſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. For Mr. <hi>S—</hi> he was ſo far from giving any partial account, that he did not ſo much as poſitively ſay, you had left our Communion. I confeſs upon a vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſuſpicion (for which we had other grounds) I took the freedom to tell you (what would fall under every ordinary ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion,) that your departure would unavoidably expoſe you unto cenſure. That ſome would impute it to a hot head, others to a weak Judgment, and a third ſort perhaps to diſcontent, that you were not gratified according to your great merits. Herein, Sir, I only plaid the part of a Rehearſal. For my own part, in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41190:5"/>imputing what I had heard of you to a fit of the Spleen, I gave an evidence of my Charity, in regard you had formerly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd of ſuch a fit as had unhing'd your faculties and ſtifled your Pen into a long ſilence; and ſure, I could never reckon that for a fault in you, which I knew to be your infelicity and affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Hitherto therefore my carriage was very innocent. And (when I long'd ſo much to hear from you) if I were a little im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient at the diſappointment, yet a little ingenuity would have given it a better interpretation than the want of common pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; and a faſt Friend would have taken it for an argument of a fincere affection. However I muſt lament my own loſs; that what you intended for my information was, by ſuch an unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate miſadventure, caſt into the common lot of waſte Paper. But whatever the conception was which thoſe Letters miſcarried with, theſe give me an intimation of your preſent change. And to queſtion whether this were <hi>Mutatio dextrae Altiſſimi,</hi> a change wrought by the right hand of the Moſt High, were, no doubt, in your Judgment to make a breach upon Charity and Prudence both together. Yet ſeeing you applaud your ſelf (as all ſuch <hi>Proſelytes</hi> uſe to do) that you have changed <hi>Opinion</hi> into <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Doubtfulneſs</hi> into <hi>Infallibility;</hi> give me leave, for once, to enquire into the real advantage, you flatter your ſelf to have purchaſed by your Separation from us. In order hereto I pray reſolve me where the Infallibility is lodged, which you ſo much boaſt of; I preſume you will not ſay, you have it in your own boſom; for that would ſmell a little too rank of arrogance; if you ſay, 'tis lodged in the perſon of the Pope, that is rendred very improbable; becauſe it was not long ſince one of them profeſſed that he was no Theologue, and conſequently not fit to determine a point of Faith; and if we may believe ſome of the <hi>Roman</hi> Writers (beſides Schiſm) Hereſy, Infidelity and Atheiſm, have been found amongſt them. And this Doctrine is ſo falſe and ſcandalous, that Mr. <hi>White</hi> makes it more criminal and dainnable than deſtouring of holy Virgins upon the Holy Altar<note n="†" place="margin">Vide T. bulae Suffragia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les.</note>.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If you place your Infallibility in the diffuſive body of the Clergy, or of Chriſtians in general, That will be of no more
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41190:5"/>advantage to the determination of Controverſies than the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Spirit, that is utterly unprofitable and uſeleſs; for why may we not find it then, in Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> as well as in <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> in Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi> as well as in <hi>Cajetan,</hi> and in Dr. <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> as well as in <hi>Stapleton?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. If you lodge it in General Councils, there we are ready to joyn iſſue with you. For thoſe which are truly ſuch, we have the greater veneration for. And I will give you one inſtance in matter of Faith, that ſhall make it evident beyond contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, (for matter of Juriſdiction afterward.) <q>In the Third general Council held at <hi>Epheſus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Concil. 3. Generale Epheſ. ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit. Can. 7. Juſtell. Codex Canon. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ. Can. 177.</note> 
                  <hi>Decrevit Sauct a Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> licere cuiquam aliam fidem afferre, vel ſcribere, vel com ponere praeter cam, quae à Sanctis Patribus Nicaeae Congregatis, in Sancto Spiritu deſinita eſt—&amp;c.</hi> The Holy Synod hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed, That it ſhall not be lawful for any one to bring in or alledge, to write or compoſe any other Faith beſides that which is defined by the Holy Fathers aſſembled at <hi>Nice,</hi> with the (aſſiſtance of the) Holy Ghoſt.</q> This Canon, which the Church of <hi>England</hi> obſerves inviolable, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth egregiouſly prevaricate; witneſs the Faith compoſed, after the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> by Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the Fourth, which is ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly ſworn by all the Clergy in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> at this day. If you ſay, this was not another Faith, nor any addition to the Ancient Creed, but only an <hi>explication</hi> of it, the very letter of that <hi>Symbol</hi> will evince the contrary; and to uſe your own expreſſion, that defence dwindles into more Evaſion. Let the Reader judge by the matter of Fact and the Obſervations following.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Confeſſion of Faith, by Pope</hi> Pius, <hi>according to the Council of</hi> Trent <hi>ſet forth</hi> — 1564.</p>
            <p>
               <q>1 <hi>A. B.</hi> do ſtedfaſtly believe and profeſs, all and ſingular the Contents of that Symbol of Faith which the holy <hi>Roman</hi> Church uſeth; That is to ſay,</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I believe in one God the Father Almighty, maker of Heaven and Earth, and of all things viſible and inviſible, and in one Lord
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41190:6"/>Jeſus Chriſt, the only begotten Son of God, begotten of the Father before all worlds, God of God, light of light, very God of very God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Nice</hi> conſiſted of 318 Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops from all parts of the World, Eaſt and Weſt, and was held in the year 325. And of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> M. the Tenth. The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Trent</hi> was not held till the year 1545. and ended not till 1563. wherein were in all, with Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals, Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bots and Proctors, but 255. and moſt of them <hi>Italians</hi> &amp; the Popes Creatures. <hi>Lud. Bail. Sum. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cil. Tom</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 600. <hi>B.</hi> 1. <hi>Edit. Pariſ.</hi> 1659.</note> 
               <hi>begotten not made, being of one ſubſtance with the Father, by whom all things were made; who for us men and for our ſalvation came down from heaven, and was incarnate by the Holy Ghoſt of the Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>and was made man; and was crucified alſo for us under</hi> Pontius Pilate, <hi>he ſuffered, and was buried, and roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain the third day according to the Scriptures, and aſcended into Heaven, and ſitteth on the right hand of God the Father; and he ſhall come again with Glory to judge both the quick and the dead: whoſe Kingdom ſhall have no end. And I believe in the Holy Ghoſt, the Lord and giver of life, who proceedeth from the Father and the Son: who with the Father and the Son together is worſhipped and glorified, who ſpake by the Prophets. And I believe one Catholick and Apoſtolick Church: I acknowledge one Baptiſm for the remiſſion of ſins; and I look for the Reſurrection of the dead, and the life of the World to come.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <p>[Thus far is the Faith of the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> to which the Pope adds theſe Articles following:]</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I do ſtedfaſtly admit and embrace Apostolical and Eccleſiaſtical Traditions, with the reſt of the Obſervations and Conſtitutions of the ſame Church. I admit alſo of the holy Scripture, according to that ſenſe, which hath been held, and is held by the holy Mother the Church whoſe office it is to judge of the true ſenſe and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of the Holy Scriptures: Nor will I ever receive or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret the ſame, but according to the unanimous conſent of the Fathers. I profeſs alſo, that there are ſeven Sacraments of the new Law, truly and properly ſo called, inſtituted by Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, and neceſſary to the Salvation of Mankind, though all of them be not neceſſary for every man; That is to ſay,</hi> Baptiſm, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, <hi>the</hi> Euchariſt, Penance, Extreme Unction, Orders, <hi>and</hi> Matrimony: <hi>and that they do confer Grace; and amongſt theſe, that Baptiſm, Confirmation, and Orders, cannot be repeated without Sacriledge. I do alſo receive and admit all the received and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Rites of the Catholick Church in the ſolemn adminiſtration of all the aforeſaid Sacraments. I do receive and embrace all and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41190:6"/>ſingular the things which were defined by the holy Synod of</hi> Trent, <hi>concerning Original Sin and Juſtification: I profeſs likewiſe, that in the Sacrifice of the Maſs there is offer'd unto God a true, proper, and propitiatory Sacrifice for the living and dead; and that in the moſt holy Sacrament of the Euchariſt, there is verily, really and ſubstantially the Body and Bloud, together with the Soul and Divinity of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; and that there is made (therein) a change of the whole ſubſtance of the Bread into his body, and of the whole ſubſtance of the Wine into his bloud; which change the Catholick Church calls</hi> Tranſubſtantiation. <hi>I do alſo confeſs, that Chriſt whole and entire, and the true Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is received in either kind alone. I do ſtedfaſtly hold, that there is a Purgatory, and that the Souls detained therein are relieved by the Suffrages of the Faithful. Likewiſe alſo, that the Saints reigning together with Chriſt, are to be worſhipped and prayed unto; and that they do offer up prayers unto God for us. And that their Reliques are to be had in veneration. I do moſt ſtedfaſtly affirm, that the Images of Chriſt, of the (Bleſſed) Virgin, the Mother of God, and of other Saints, are to be had and kept, and a due honour and veneration to be given unto them. Alſo, that the power of Indulgences was left by Chriſt unto his Church; and I affirm, that the uſe of them is very ſalutary (and beneficial) to Chriſtian people: I acknowledge the holy Catholick and Apoſtolick</hi> Roman <hi>Church to be the Mother and Miſtreſs of all Churches. And I promiſe and ſwear true obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Pope of</hi> Rome, <hi>ſucceſſor to B.</hi> Peter, <hi>Prince of the Apoſtles, and the Vicar of Chriſt. I do alſo undoubtedly receive and profeſs all things elſe, which are delivered, defined and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by the ſacred Canons and general Councils, and eſpecially by the moſt holy Synod of</hi> Trent. <hi>And I do likewiſe condemn, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject and anathematize all things that are contrary, and all Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies whatſoever, which are condemned, rejected and anathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized by the Church. This true Catholick Faith, without which no man can be ſaved, which at this preſent I do freely profeſs and truly hold, by Gods help, I will moſt conſtantly to the very laſt breath of my life, intirely and inviolably hold and confeſs the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41190:7"/>ſame, and take care, as much as in me lies, that the ſame ſhall be held, taught and preached by all my Subjects, or all thoſe under my care and charge, in reſpect of my Function. This I</hi> A. B. <hi>do promiſe, vow, and ſwear. So God be my help, and theſe his holy Goſpels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the Creed of Pope <hi>Pius,</hi> according to the Council of <hi>Trent.</hi> Now betwixt theſe Articles and thoſe of the Church of <hi>England</hi> there is a vaſt difference, both 1. In the <hi>matter;</hi> and 2. In the <hi>impoſition;</hi> and 3. In the end of them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the <hi>Matter</hi> of theſe Articles: Thoſe of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are not to be believed as Articles of Faith, no further than they can approve themſelves to be contained in the holy Scriptures; for thus we are taught in the Sixth of theſe Articles.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Holy Scripture containeth all things neceſſary to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo that whatſoever is not read therein, nor may be proved thereby<note n="*" place="margin">Licet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdum à fidelibus ut pium &amp; conducibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile ad or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem &amp; decorum admitta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>In the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin of that Article.</hi>
                  </note>, is not to be required of any man, that it ſhould be belived as an Article of the Faith, or be thought requiſite or neceſſary to ſalvation.</q> But amongſt the Articles of Faith enjoyed by Pope <hi>Pius,</hi> ſome are quite beſide the Holy Scripture, ſome againſt it; ſome are mere ſpeculations of the Schools, and others but probable, and matters of doubtful diſputation. For inſtance; (1) The multiplication of <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocates</hi> and Ghoſtly Patrons: (2) The Sacrifice of the <hi>Maſs:</hi> (3) The Adoration of the <hi>Hoſt:</hi> (4) The power of <hi>Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences;</hi> as they are maintained and practiſed in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Theſe are, at leaſt beſides the Holy Scripture.</p>
            <p n="1">(1) The <hi>Invocation</hi> of Saints, and veneration of Images (as practiſed generally by the Common people, according to their Books.)</p>
            <p n="2">(2) The publick Service of the Church in an <hi>unknown</hi> Tongue. The adminiſtration of the Lords Supper, ordinarily to the people, but in <hi>one</hi> kind: And that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is the <hi>Mother</hi> and <hi>Miſtreſs</hi> of all other Churches. Theſe are againſt Scripture.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:41190:7"/>
            <p n="3">(3) <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> (whatſoever it ſignifies more than a <hi>Real preſence,</hi> and the benefits which flow from it) with the unaccountable hypotheſes which depend upon it: And <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory,</hi> as it is blown up into Climaerical flames by the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; with the means and manner of deliverance out of it, are no better than Scholaſtical ſpeculations. And many of the reſt valued but as probabilities, or matters of doubtful diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the <hi>impoſition</hi> of theſe reſpective Articles the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is vaſt. For thoſe of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> we have not only, <q>I receive, admit and embrace (this Faith;) not only, I do affirm and aknowledge, conſtantly hold and moſt ſtedfaſtly aſſert it: not only, I do with a ſtedfaſt Faith believe and profeſs it; but under the high and ſolemn obligation, I do promiſe, vow, and ſwear, to hold, teach and preach the ſame to the very laſt breath of my life, and to procure all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers under my charge to do the like.</q> But to the Articles of Religion in the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſubſcription is only required, without any obligation to teach, profeſs or aſſert them, further than they are contained in the Holy Scripture, or may be proved thereby to be Articles of the Faith; or admitted for diſcipline and good order. And it is moreover to be obſerved, That his Majeſty in his Declaration before theſe Articles printed 1630, though he forbids the offering violence to the liberal and Grammatical ſenſe of theſe Articles; yet he ſeems to allow a modeſt liberty (without contention) in putting the moſt favourable conſtruction upon them. The words are theſe, <q>Though ſome differences have been ill raiſed; yet we take comfort in this, that all Clergy-men within our Realm, have always moſt willingly ſubſcribed to the Articles eſtabliſhed; which is an Argument to Us, that they all agree in the true literal meaning of the ſaid Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles: and that even in thoſe curious points, in which the preſent differences lie, Men of all ſorts take the Articles of the Church of <hi>England</hi> to be for them; which is an Argument, that none of them intend any deſertion of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41190:8"/>Articles eſtabliſhed.</q> Where we ſee his <hi>Majeſty</hi> took notice, that men of all ſorts took theſe Articles to be for them; and he declares, that he took comfort therein. Which argues, that the impoſition was not ſtrict and rigid as to the ſenſe and meaning of the Articles. And though in the <hi>Synod</hi> 1640. <hi>Can.</hi> 6. an Oath was enjoyned; yet it was with as much modeſty and tenderneſs, as any ſober and peaceable Subject can deſire: for thus it runs, <hi>I</hi> A. B. <hi>do ſwear, that I do approve the Doctrine and Diſcipline, or Government in the Church of</hi> England, <hi>as containing all things neceſſary to ſalvation.</hi> Where two things are very obſervable, (1) The aſſertion is only this, That I do approve the Doctrine, &amp;c. the (2) Only as containing all things neceſſary to ſalvation; for which we are referred to the authority of the Holy Scripture by the Sixth Article, as was obſerved before.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As to the <hi>end</hi> of theſe reſpective Articles; Thoſe of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> are declared to be neceſſary to ſalvation, not only <hi>Neceſſitate praecepti, ſed Medii;</hi> neceſſary as well upon the account of a Means as of a Precept: for the Pope declares, <hi>Hanc (eſſe) veram Catholicam fidem, Extra quam nemo ſalvus eſse poteſt.</hi> 
               <q>That this is the true Catholick Faith, without which no man can be ſaved.</q> But the Articles of the Church of <hi>England</hi> generally are intended for a <hi>decorum</hi> and <hi>order</hi> (matters of neceſſary Faith being herein reſtrained to the Holy Scriptures) to keep out diſputes and vain jangling, and to preſerve peace and concord in her Communion. Thus much is intimated in the very Title prefix'd to thoſe Articles; but much more clearly in his Majeſties Declaration before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, where he ſaith, <q>We hold it moſt agreeable to our Kingly Office and our own Religious Zeal, to conſerve and maintain the Church committed to our charge in the unity of the true Religion, and in the bond of peace, and not to ſuffer unneceſſary Diſputations, Alterations, or Queſtions to be raiſed, which may nouriſh Faction both in the Church and Commonwealth. We have therefore thought fit to make this Declaration, That the Articles, &amp;c. do contain
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41190:8"/>the true Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> agreeable to Gods word; which we do therefore ratifie and confirm, &amp;c.</q> But this is more clear in a Book ſet forth 1571. called, <hi>Liber quorundam Canonum Diſciplinae Eccleſiae</hi> Anglicanae <hi>SS. de Concio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natoribus.</hi> Where it is ordered thus: <hi>Imprimis vero vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <q>Let the Preachers take care, that they teach no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in their Sermons, which they would have the People hold and believe as a matter of Religion; but what is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to the Doctrine of the Old or New Teſtament, and what the Catholick Fathers and Ancient Biſhops have ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of the ſame. And becauſe thoſe Articles of Chriſtian Religion, which were agreed upon by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, &amp;c. are without doubt collected out of the Sacred Books of the Old and New Teſtament, and do in all things agree with the heavenly Doctrine contained therein: Alſo, becauſe the Book of Common Prayers, and the Book of the Inauguration of Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons, do contain nothing that is contrary to that Doctrine; who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall be ſent out to teach the People, ſhall confirm the authority and belief of thoſe Articles, as well by their ſubſcription as in their Sermons. <hi>Qui ſecus fecerit &amp; contrariâ doctrinâ Populum turbaverit, excommunicabitur;</hi> Whoſoever ſhall do otherwiſe, and diſturb the People with any contrary Doctrine ſhall be excommunicated.</q> Here indeed the Clergy are implicitly enjoyned to preach up the belief and authority of theſe Articles: But withal, (1) The belief and authority of them is required, not as grounded upon the <hi>Declaration</hi> and <hi>Sanction</hi> of the Eccleſiaſtical Governours (though a hearty ſubmiſſion and obedience is due thereto in matters of Religion, Diſcipline, and Order, upon the account of a Divine precept,) but upon their <hi>Congruity</hi> with the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> according to the ſenſe of the Ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. (2) That ſuch as tranſgreſs theſe Articles are puniſh'd (for want of good manners) as <hi>diſturbers</hi> of the publick Peace.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41190:9"/>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore, though the Author of the <hi>Guide in Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies*</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Diſc. 3. cap. 7.</note>, hath made it his buſineſs to ſtrain every Sentence, Phraſe, and word in the Canons as well as the Articles of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to make thoſe Articles ſeem to run parallel in the Charge of a <hi>new</hi> Impoſition of Faith, with thoſe in the Creed of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the Fourth aforementioned; yet, by what hath been obſerved, it is evident, that the Articles of the Church of <hi>England</hi> were not intended (as thoſe of that Pope clearly were) for an <hi>Addition</hi> to the Faith declared by the Fathers at <hi>Nice,</hi> which (with all Chriſtian Churches) we profeſs as <hi>Catholicks;</hi> but for <hi>information</hi> to direct our publick diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes generally as occaſion ſerves, in matters of Religion, as we are <hi>united</hi> in the <hi>Communion</hi> of the <hi>particular</hi> Church of <hi>England,</hi> after a deliberate and ſober <hi>Reformation;</hi> which to attempt and perform, as far as in them lies, no doubt all Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops are as well obliged in duty by Chriſt's Command, [<hi>Apoc.</hi> 2 <hi>&amp;</hi> 3 <hi>Cap.</hi>] as preſcribed to do it orderly, by the 34. of the Apoſtles Canons<note n="†" place="margin">Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos uniuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cujuſque gentis noſſe oportet eum, qui in eis eſt primus, &amp; exiſtimare eum ut caput: &amp; nihil facere magni momenti, praeter illius ſententiam: illa autem ſola facere unumquemque quae ad ſuam paroeciam pertinent, &amp; pagos qui ei ſubfunt.</note>.</p>
            <p>To leave this long, though not unneceſſary digreſſion; This <hi>Infallibility</hi> (in the latitude the <hi>Roman</hi> party pleads for) is ſo very improbable, that Mr. <hi>Creſſey</hi> (in his <hi>Neophytiſm</hi>) was not able to ſwallow it till he had ſhrunk it up into an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defectibility;</hi> wherein we can heartily cloſe with him. And for all that great priviledge, which make ſo much noiſe in the world, I do very well obſerve, that in many caſes they are glad to reſt ſatisfied with a <hi>probable Conſcience.</hi> And in ſpight of that Infallibility, They muſt ſtand to the courteſie or ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of a <hi>probable Opinion,</hi> to ſecure themſelves (according to their practice) from the peril of Idolatry. And this is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by the Jeſuite <hi>Ant. Terill,</hi> our Countryman, in his Tractate <hi>de Conſcientia Probabili:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Edit. Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dii, 1668. p. 387, &amp;c.</note> His words are theſe; <q>
                  <hi>Quid magis ad mores, &amp;c.</hi> What does more concern man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41190:9"/>and the ſtrictneſs of the Law of Nature, than that the worſhip due to God be not beſtowed upon a Creature; and yet it is lawful many times, out of a probable Opinion only, to beſtow Divine worſhip upon the Euchariſt, and to adore God when he is but probably latent there. For there is no true certainty; but only a Probability, that this numerical Hoſt is rightly conſecrated. Firſt, It is not certain that he who did conſecrate was a Prieſt, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not certain that he was baptized, as alſo, becauſe it is not certain that he was (lawfully or) validly Ordained by a true Biſhop, having an intention requiſite to that ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, &amp;c. Secondly, It is not certain that he did pronounce the words of Conſecration. If he did duly pronounce them, yet Thirdly, perhaps he had not a due intention. If all theſe things were (obſerved) as they ſhould be, It is not certain, in the Fourth place, that a due matter was made uſe of; for the Bread might not be made of Wheat. Fifth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Although all theſe things proceeded well and rightly; yet it is not indubitable, that the Officer to whom the cuſtody of the venerable Sacrament belongs, did not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe an Hoſt that was not conſecrated, inſtead of one that was (truly conſecrated) to be adored. All theſe are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals, to which we may add the malice of mans heart, which is too vigorous in ſome perſons. Upon theſe heads <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> we have known many Cheats too frequently practiſed in this matter; and they know it much better, who are employed as Judges upon the Tribunal of the Sacred Inquiſition.</q> 
               <hi>Thus far Father</hi> Terill.</p>
            <p>Now, if they of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> have no certainty in their Sacraments, no certainty in their Sacrifice of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, no certainty in their Prieſthood, no certainty, but they may commit Idolatry every day; if they cannot be certain, but the malice of their Prieſts may fruſtrate all the ſacred Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of God to them, and make them abſolutely null, though they be never ſo worthily diſpoſed to receive the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of them: (And this is the Doctrine and Belief commonly
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41190:10"/>maintained in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>) They ſhould rather bluſh at ſuch an Infallibility, than boaſt of any great advantage to be reaped from it. For grant further, that that Infallibility were ſuch as they would have it, yet they can have no <hi>ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> in it for ſalvation. 'Tis ſuch as a man may carry into <hi>Hell</hi> with him (if it proves not a means to lead him thither,) where (for ought I know) the Devils have it as much as he. And <hi>Gregory</hi> the Seventh was of the ſame mind; <hi>Nam,</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>ut</hi> Jacobus <hi>frater Domini teſtatur, fides ſine operibus mortua eſt, qualem &amp; Daemones habere fatetur; Non Ergo minùs eſt reſiſtendum pertinacibus authenticarum inſtitutionum im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnatoribus quam Sacrae fidei violatoribus, cùm &amp; Daemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus aſſimilentur quicunque inſtitutionem SS. Patrum in fide tantum, &amp; non etiam in converſatione pro viribus aſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctatur?</hi> For as <hi>James,</hi> the Brother of our Lord, doth te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſie, <hi>Faith without Works is dead,</hi> which kind of Faith he doth acknowledge to be in the Devils. We ought there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no leſs to reſiſt ſuch as are obſtinate impugners of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick Inſtitutions (<hi>viz.</hi> of Piety) than ſuch as do vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the Sacred Faith, ſeeing they that do earneſtly follow the inſtruction of the Holy Fathers in (matter of) Faith only, and not in (a holy) converſation are like unto the Devils.</q> For this <hi>Infallibility</hi> is reſtrained to matters of Faith, and that Faith is but <hi>hiſtorical</hi> (as they call it) and not ſufficient to ſalvation. <q>To the Eſſence of a Church, right Doctrines in Practicals are as neceſſary as in Specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, if mortal Sin excludes from ſalvation, as well as an erroneous Faith<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>R. H.</hi> Diſc. of the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Church Guides. p. 82.</note>; as the Author of <hi>the Guide in Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies</hi> does acknowledge.</q> And this is the Doctrine of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> Seſſ. 6. de Juſtificatione: <q>
                  <hi>Si quis dixerit, ſolâ fide juſtificari, ita ut intelligat nihil aliud requiri quod ad Juſtificationis gratiam conſequendam cooperetur, &amp; nulla ex parte neceſſe eſſe cum ſuae voluntatis motu praeparari atque diſponi, Anathema ſit,</hi> Can. 9. If any man ſhall ſay, that Faith alone does Juſtifie, ſo that nothing elſe is required to cooperate towards the attainment of the Grace of Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41190:10"/>and that it is in no wiſe neceſſary that he ſhould be prepared and diſpoſed (to it) by any motion of his own will, let him be accurſed. <hi>Et</hi> Can. 19. <hi>Siquis dixerit, nihil praeceptum eſſe in Evangelio praeter fidem, caetera eſſe indifferentia, neque praecepta neque prohibita, ſed libera; aut Decem Praecepta nihil pertinere ad Chriſtianos, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema ſit.</hi> If any man ſhall ſay, there is nothing command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Goſpel, but Faith; that all other matters are indifferent, neither commanded nor forbidden, but left free: or that the Ten Commandements do not concern Chriſtians; let him be accurſed. <hi>Et</hi> Can. 21. <hi>Si quis di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erit Chriſtum Jeſum à Deo hominibus datum fuiſſe, ut Redemptorem, cui fidant, non etiam ut Legiſlatorem, cui obediant; Anathema ſit:</hi> that is, If any man ſhall ſay, that Chriſt Jeſus was given unto man of God, as a Redeemer in whom they ſhould truſt, and not alſo as a Lawgiver, whom they ſhould obey; let him be accurſed.</q> (Which Canons we can readily ſubſcribe to:) From which it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears beyond exception, that the Infallibility pretended by the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is not to be relied on as ſufficient for ſalvation. <q>The Creeds chiefly comprehending Specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, there muſt be a great body of Articles alſo of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Faith relating to Practicals; as <hi>R. H.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">C. 1. §. 3. p 4.</note> maintains in his Diſcourſe of the <hi>Neceſſity of Church Guides.</hi>
               </q> But doth this Infallibility extend to all matters of Practical belief, as well as Speculative? Yes, ſaith <hi>R. H. Chriſt hath left an Infallible Guide for Manners as well as Faith</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Id. p. 176</note>; and a little after, <hi>God hath provided by the ſame Church Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to preſerve his Church in truth, and to reſtrain it from ſin; giving an equal Commiſſion to teach the ignorant, and to correct the vicious. And that ſince their Doctrine directs our Manners, as well as Faith; their Infallibility is as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for things of Practice, as of Speculation.</hi> But if there be ſuch an Infallibility in the Guides of the Church, not o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly in reference to points of Faith, but to Doctrines of Practice alſo,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.14.</note> 
               <hi>What meaneth then this bleating of the Sheep
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41190:11"/>in mine ears, and this lowing of the Oxen, which I hear?</hi> Of the degeneracy of the Church in his time <hi>V. Bede</hi> writes thus:<note place="margin">Apud <hi>Meiſner</hi> de Eccleſia. p. 681, 682, 684.</note> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Videt quiſque non ſine lachrymis, &amp;c.</hi> Every one ſees not without tears, into what a weak and infirm con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition the ſtate of the Church does daily dwindle.</q> And St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> in his time; <q>
                  <hi>Hodie ſerpit putida tabes, &amp;c.</hi> Now-a-days an infectious and ſpreading Conſumption hath ſeized the body of the Church, which the further it is dilated the more deſperate it grows; and it is ſo much the more dangerous, by how much the more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</q> And after him the Cardinal, <hi>Petrus de Aliaco,</hi> in a publick Sermon at the Council of <hi>Conſtans. Manifeſtum</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>eſſe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 'Tis apparent, that the Church hath of a long time been in ſeveral reſpects deformed, and not only hath (in time paſt) but doth now extreamly want a reformation as well in Faith as Manners.</q> The like complaints are made in theſe our days; not againſt the corrupt Manners of wicked men only, but againſt the <hi>New Extravagant</hi> and <hi>pernicious</hi> Doctrines, which do lead to, and incourage ſuch ill Manners: witneſs what was lately written by <hi>Macarius Havermans</hi> Canon of the Church of St. <hi>Michael, Ordinis praemonſtratenſis,</hi> in his <hi>Tyrocinium Chriſtianae Moralis Theologiae</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Printed at <hi>Antwerp</hi> An. 1674.</note>. Where, in his Epiſtle <hi>Dedicatory</hi> to the <hi>Abbot,</hi> writing of the (unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily) <hi>fertile</hi> Age into which we are fallen; he ſaith thus, <q>
                  <hi>Quot Theologias Morales non edidit, &amp;c.</hi> How many Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtems of Moral Divinity hath this Age brought forth, which are as ſo many whimſical fictions and opinions of Divines, grounded upon philoſophical Arguments, ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with curious and exquiſite probabilities, and big with humane inventions.</q> And in his Preface to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der he complains of the Arrogance of theſe new Doctors, in preferring their own Sentiments before the Doctrine of the Ancient Fathers, Councils, and Holy Scriptures: <q>
                  <hi>Hinc vix ullum,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whence it comes to pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, that in their Writings you ſhall ſcarce find any place of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41190:11"/>Sacred Scripture, or the Ancient Councils, or Holy Fathers alledged; but they weight every thing in the ballance of their own underſtanding: And thus for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Divinity (whoſe concluſions concerning God and his Attributes, &amp;c. ought to be deduced from the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erring and uncontrollable Doctrine of Gods word, and from the moſt ſecure Decrees of the Holy Fathers) they ſet up a Natural Theology or Philoſophy grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Principles of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and his Followers, whoſe Authority they alledge more frequently than that of St. <hi>Ambroſe, Jerome, Auſtin,</hi> or any other Holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; not to ſay they do more value them: nay, ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted are they to their own Inventions, that a plauſible Reaſon of their own ſhall be preferr'd before the graveſt Sentiments and Maxims of the Holy Fathers.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Hereupon <hi>Caramuel</hi> breaks out into that ingenuous ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment, <q>I ſpend not much time, or rather loſe it not, in turning over the Writings of the Ancients.</q> 
               <hi>And gives us his reaſon elſewhere,</hi> Becauſe, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> as to <q>Manners the Opinions of the Moderns are to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd to thoſe of the Ancients. For as a late Writer hath it <hi>[in novae libertatis explicatione]</hi> the Modern Schoolmen had a greater inſight into things, than the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. And have alſo thought fit to reject whatſoever they approved or looked upon as not improbable: And <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> now, who ſees not at the firſt glance, that thoſe exorbitant Tenents are ſo abhorring from the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of Antiquity, that they need no conſutation; but that barely to mention them is to confute them? So that, to ſpeak with St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> I think them fitter to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailed by Believers, than diſputed againſt by me. Their clamours will ſooner be drowned by Prayers and Tears, than by the noiſe of Arguments: And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt we ſhall do more advantage for ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, if with our Prayers we endeavour their refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, leſt they periſh with their great Wits, or
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41190:12"/>ruine others with their damnable preſumption. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, this ſlighting of the Holy Fathers is like to be very, pernicious to the Church; for if their Authority be ſo diſeſteemed and undervalued in matter of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and that by <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Writers, who can blame the Hereticks for not valuing their Authority in matters of Faith? for why ſhould they be valued in matters of Faith, more than in matters of Manners? Are not Manners to be directed by the Authority of Divine Tradition, as well as Faith? Are not the Faithful as well Truſtees of the Tradition of Manners, as of Faith?</q> And a little after he exhorts his Reader thus: <hi>Pro para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxo</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>ergo reputamus, &amp;c.</hi> Wherefore let us account that of a late Writer for a mere paradox <hi>(viz.) [Tota Theologia Moralis eſt nova]</hi> All Moral Divinity is whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly New. For if it be <hi>New,</hi> then it was not delivered by Chriſt, nor by his Apoſtles, nor by the Holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: And conſequently, neither Chriſtian, nor Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical, nor Orthodoxal; and that which is more, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it true, nor genuine; but ſpurious and adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate, and for that reaſon not to be applauded, but condemned, not to be embraced, but baniſhed, not to be alledged, but exploded. <hi>Tantum enim à veteri ſimplicitate, &amp;c. (as it follows a little aftey)</hi> For we have ſo far ſtarted from the Primitive ſimplicity and Obedience, that there is ſcarce any Law but is rendred uſeleſs by the gloſſes of the Schoolmen, as it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, if we pleaſe to trace them in ſome particular Laws: Of what great efficacy (I pray) will that Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Law be, concerning Anniverſary Confeſſion and Communion, if it may be ſatisfied by a bare ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal, though ſacrilegious Communion and Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion? Nevertheleſs, that a man may ſatisfie that Precept by ſuch a ſacrilegious Communion, many Schoolmen, <hi>de facto,</hi> do ſtill teach. Again, of what force is that Law about hearing the Sacred Offices on the Lords
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41190:12"/>day, and other Holy-days, if that Command may be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied only by an external preſence of the body; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though during the whole time of the Sacrifice a man ſuffers his mind voluntarily to wander and be diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and taken up with impure and filthy Cogitations? And yet many Schoolmen teach this Doctrine. The Law for the obſervation of Faſting, how unprofitable it is rendred, is very notably ſet forth by <hi>Marchantius</hi> in the Complaint of (his perſonated) Sr. <hi>Jejunium</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Querimonia S. Jejunii, <hi>by</hi> Marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius.</note>. The like may be ſhewed in other Inſtances.</q> 
               <hi>Thus for Havermans.</hi> By all which we ſee the fruits of this great priviledge of Infallibility in the Church of <hi>Rome; viz.</hi> by their own Confeſſion they have entertain'd a new Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral<note n="†" place="margin">See <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taltius</hi>'s Provincial Letters, with <hi>Wen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorchius</hi>'s Notes upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them. <hi>Latinè Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon.</hi> 1678.</note> (and not the Primitive) for matters of Practice; and in our obſervation, they have done the like in matters of Faith and Speculation. And when we find ſo great a variation, we muſt needs conclude, That either the Ancient Church was not <hi>then;</hi> or elſe, That the preſent Church (which differs ſo much from it) is not <hi>now</hi> Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible.</p>
            <p>And now the Queſtion may be put, Which particular Church is in the more <hi>ſafe</hi> condition? In the Church of <hi>England</hi> we have <hi>The Faith of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as St. <hi>James</hi> calls it, (<hi>James</hi> 2.1.) we have St. <hi>Peters</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (1 <hi>Peter</hi> 3.15.) his <hi>Rationale</hi> of the Chriſtian hope. We have St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Depoſitum,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.20.<note place="margin">Quid eſt Depoſitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? id eſt, quod tibi creditum eſt, non quod à te inventum, Quod ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptiſti, non quod excogitaſti. Rem non ingenii, ſed doctrinae. Non uſurpationis privatae, ſed publicae traditionis. Rem ad te perductam, non à te prólatam, in qua non Author debes eſſe, ſed Cuſtos; non inſtitutor, ſed ſectator: non ducens, ſed ſequens. <hi>Vincent. Lirinenſis.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and form of ſound words,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. And it is undoubtedly St. <hi>Judes</hi> Faith we <hi>contend</hi> for, which, as <hi>Beza</hi> very well notes upon the place, was <hi>once,</hi> (and <hi>at once</hi>) <hi>ſo delivered</hi> to the Saints, that it ought never to be <hi>changed.</hi> That Faith which the Fathers of the Council
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41190:13"/>of <hi>Nice</hi> profeſſed we do very heartily embrace; we keep this Faith <hi>whole</hi> and <hi>undefiled.</hi> But from receiving any other, we are deterred by the Sentence of the Synod of <hi>Epheſus</hi> forementioned; <q>
                  <hi>Qui aliam fidem audent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponere, &amp;c.</hi> Whoſoever ſhall dare to compoſe, alledge or introduce any other Faith, if he be a Biſhop or Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy-man, he ſhall be degraded; if a Lay-man, excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated.</q> If the Faith thus delivered were ſufficient for their ſalvation <hi>(in genere fidei)</hi> why not for ours? And herein, without all doubt, we are no leſs <hi>Infallible</hi> than the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> And to the Ancient Fathers in the moſt Sacred Councils, this was their<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lud. Bail.</hi> Sum. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. Tom. 1. in decreto de Symbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo. <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 3. <hi>m. pa.</hi> 522.</note> 
               <hi>Shield</hi> againſt all Hereſies, <hi>Quo ſolo,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Through whoſe attractive power alone they have, in times paſt, drawn unbelievers to the Faith, reſiſted and rooted out Hereticks, and confirm'd the Faithful;</hi> as the Fathers of the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge. If there be any other points of Faith need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to ſalvation, our ignorance thereof (after a long and diligent ſearch) is both <hi>involuntary</hi> and <hi>invincible,</hi> and that will <hi>totally</hi> excuſe us.</p>
            <p>For that <hi>ſuperfatation</hi> of Articles by Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the Fourth, we were never Baptized into them, nor can we anſwer for them. The truth is, the Faith of the Church of <hi>England</hi> the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> can never juſtly reprehend, being more <hi>pure,</hi> more <hi>Primitive,</hi> and more <hi>Catholick</hi> than their own, and was profeſſed intirely by all Chriſtian Churches before ſome Articles of the preſent Church of <hi>Rome</hi> were ever known to have had a being. And for part of this we have a pregnant acknowledgment in the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> where they ſet down this <hi>Symbolum fidei totidem verbis, quibus in omnibus Eccleſiis legitur;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lud. Bail.</hi> ubi ſupra.</note> In the ſame words in which it is read in all Churches: And this they ſet down as that <hi>principle, wherein all that do profeſs the Faith of Christ do neceſſarily agree;</hi> (and) <hi>as that firm and only foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, againſt which the gates of Hell ſhall never be able to prevail.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:41190:13"/>
            <p>This Faith (I ſay) we do keep whole and undefiled; but, it ſeems, it was a foundation too narrow to bear up the <hi>Popiſh</hi> ſuperſtructures of <hi>Hay</hi> and <hi>Stubble:</hi> but yet, being the <hi>only</hi> foundation (as they confeſs,) and ſo <hi>firm,</hi> that the gates of Hell ſhall never <hi>prevail</hi> againſt it; we do ſtedfaſtly <hi>reſt</hi> upon it, <hi>building our ſelves</hi> thereon, as St.<note place="margin">Epiſt. Jude v. 20, 21.</note> 
               <hi>Jude</hi> directs us, <hi>in expectation of the mercy of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt to Eternal life.</hi> Towards the accompliſhment whereof our Charity is ſo much more <hi>Catholick</hi> than theirs, that (with ſome craft and ſophiſtry, though with little reaſon) they take an Argument from thence to delude the weak, and make them <hi>Proſelytes</hi> to their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <p>For our <hi>Agenda,</hi> or matters of Practice, we have a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy that is full, ſolemn and intelligible, we have all <hi>Sacraments</hi> and <hi>Sacramentals</hi> that are generally <hi>neceſſary,</hi> or of any <hi>efficacy</hi> to ſalvation. And (beſides all <hi>publick</hi> Offices) for <hi>private</hi> devotion and uſe, we have Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and forms of <hi>Chriſtian piety,</hi> no part of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church better. Our <hi>Prieſthood</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> you cannot, with any truth or reaſon, deny to be <hi>Apoſtolical;</hi> and if our <hi>Diſcipline</hi> be in ſome inſtances collapſed from the ſeverity which it obtained in the practice of the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients,</hi> that of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> is ſo likewiſe. And if we reflect upon the many <hi>diſadvantages</hi> and <hi>perils,</hi> which are in <hi>Their</hi> Communion, they will warrant the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity in ours to be far the greater. Amongſt the <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantages</hi> on that ſide, I reckon their <hi>half</hi> Sacraments againſt the expreſs letter of our Saviours Inſtitution<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 26.26. 1 Cor. 11.23, &amp;c.</note>; and their Service in an <hi>unknown</hi> Tongue, contrary to the expreſs diſcourſe of the Apoſtle<note place="margin">† 1. Cor. 14.</note>. Amongſt the <hi>perils,</hi> I muſt account (1) That of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> in the <hi>adoration</hi> of the <hi>Hoſt.</hi> (2) The <hi>veneration</hi> of <hi>Images:</hi> (3) And the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation</hi> of <hi>Saints.</hi> Secondly, Such as ariſe from the <hi>abuſes</hi> in the matter of <hi>Confeſſion</hi> and <hi>Penances,</hi> of <hi>Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence</hi> and <hi>Diſpenſation,</hi> with many <hi>deluſions</hi> under pretence
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41190:14"/>of <hi>Revelations.</hi> Thirdly, Such as ariſe from ſeveral of their <hi>Doctrines, viz.</hi> That the Sacrament does conferr Grace <hi>[ex opere operato]</hi> from the Act performed, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any worthy or <hi>moral</hi> diſpoſition in the Receiver. That <hi>Attrition,</hi> for fear of Hell, is ſufficient, without <hi>Charity,</hi> to obtain Grace and pardon in the Sacrament of Penance. That in a caſe of Conſcience, I may follow a <hi>probable</hi> opinion, which is more <hi>benign</hi> and <hi>gentle,</hi> and reject that which is more <hi>ſafe,</hi> if it be more <hi>ſevere</hi> and <hi>rigid.</hi> That a man is not obliged to decline and avoid, <hi>Proximam occaſionem peccandi,</hi> the immediate danger of ſinning, though he has had ſad experience of his own frailty and recidivation: That the precept of Repentance does not bind <hi>preſently,</hi> but only in the time of <hi>ſickneſs,</hi> or at the <hi>point</hi> of death. Theſe Doctrines are taught and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, without any the leaſt check of his <hi>Infallible Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor is the danger ſmall, which ariſeth from the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion of their <hi>Infallibility.</hi> For from thence proceeds a belief, that whatſoever they take upon them to <hi>define</hi> is as true as Goſpel: And what ſad work this hath made in the Church of God we may obſerve from that ſingle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance about the <hi>Sacrament.</hi> In a Council at <hi>Rome,</hi> under <hi>Nicholas</hi> the Second,<note place="margin">An. Dom. 1059.</note> 
               <hi>Berengarius</hi> was enjoyned a form of <hi>Recautation,</hi> wherein he profeſſed and ſwore, <hi>that the Bread and Wine, which are ſet upon the Altar, after Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration, are not only a Sacrament,</hi> but alſo <hi>the true Body and Blood</hi> of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. And (that the ſaid Body) is not in <hi>Sacrament</hi> only, but in <hi>truth (N. B) Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualiter manibus Sacerdotum</hi> tractari, frangi <hi>&amp; fidelium dentibus atteri,</hi> i. e. <hi>ſenſually handled by the Prieſt, broken and torn by the teeth of the Faithful.</hi> Expreſſions ſo groſs to unfold an inexplicable myſtery, that the Author of the <hi>Gloſs</hi> upon <hi>Gratian</hi> gives his Reader this ſober warning of them,<note place="margin">De confect. diſt. 2. c. 42. ego <hi>Bereng.</hi>
               </note> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Haec verba niſi ſane intelligas, in majorem incides Haereſin, quam ipſe</hi> Berengarius <hi>habuit: i. e.</hi> Unleſs you
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41190:14"/>underſtand theſe words in a ſound ſenſe, you will fall into a greater <hi>Hereſie</hi> than <hi>Berengarius</hi> was guilty of.</q> And upon the account of this pretended <hi>Infallibility,</hi> I might add ſome Reflections upon thoſe horrid <hi>Murthers, Treaſons,</hi> and <hi>Rebellions,</hi> which have been encouraged and carried on out of a belief of the Popes <hi>Supremacy</hi> and Power over Princes, at leaſt <hi>in ordine ad Spiritualia,</hi> in order to Church-matters; which muſt needs make a great flaw in their Allegiance. What think you of the Popes <hi>Nnncio</hi> at the head of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army.</p>
            <p>Sir, if you will give your ſelf the freedom impartially to conſider the Anſwers that are made by the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Writers, to excuſe what is charged upon them for theſe, and ſome other looſe Doctrines and practices, you will find it no Fable, That their <hi>defences</hi> dwindle into mere evaſions. I ſhall now conclude your trouble and my own with a few Animadverſions upon the whole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That (how hot ſoever your Zeal may grow for the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>) you might have done much better ſervice for the Church <hi>Catholick,</hi> if you had continued in the Communion of that part of it which is eſtabliſhed in this Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To uſe the word of the Ingenious Author of <hi>[The Notion of Schiſme,]</hi> that for any to deſert the Church of <hi>England</hi> to communicate with that of <hi>Rome,</hi> is ſuch a framick humor, as for a man to quit the <hi>neateſt</hi> appart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and exchange for the moſt <hi>ſluttiſh</hi> Rooms in the ſame Houſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That you have given a ſcandal to your Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> contrary to that Caveat and Admonition of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.32.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſtius</hi> ad locum.</note> And he that gives offence to his Brother, ſins againſt God, <hi>whoſe handy-work he deſtroys, Rom.</hi> 14.20. He ſins alſo againſt Chriſt, in deſtroying him <hi>for whom Chriſt died, Rom.</hi> 14.15.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:41190:15"/>
            <p>Fourthly and Laſtly, That by withdrawing your ſelf from that ſubjection and obedience, which by the Laws of the Catholick Church you owe to your own Biſhop, Primate, or Metropolitan, you run deſperately into <hi>Schiſme,</hi> while you are ſuperſtitiouſly ſolicitous to avoid it. For <q>
                  <hi>Schiſma eſt contumax adverſus Epiſcopum rebehio, quâ quis ejus communionem deſerit, &amp;c.</hi> Schiſme is a plain Rebellion againſt the Biſhop, whereby a man forſakes his Communion and endures no fellowſhip with him in Divine matters; as <hi>Chriſtian Lupus</hi> hath it upon <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Schol. ad cap 6. de praeſcript. Epiſt. 65.</note>.</q> And St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> in an Epiſtle <hi>ad Rogatianum No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venſem,</hi> who had been affronted by his <hi>Deacon,</hi> ſaith thus: <q>
                  <hi>Haec ſunt initia Haereticorum, &amp;c.</hi> By theſe means He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks are hatched, and the endeavours of ill-minded Schiſmaticks promoted; who, that they may gratifie their humorſome whymfies, do ſupercilionſly contemn him that is ſet over them: thus men depart from the Church, and ſet up a prophane Altar (that is a <hi>Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle</hi>) without (the Communion of it): Thus they make war upon the Peace left by Chriſt, and rebel againſt Unity and the Ordinance of God.</q> And <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 69. <hi>ad Florentium Pupianum,</hi> writing in reference to himſelf, he ſaith thus: <q>
                  <hi>Inde Schiſmata &amp; Haereſes abortae ſunt &amp; oriuntur, &amp;c.</hi> Hence Hereſies and Schiſmes have their riſe; when as the Biſhop, who is but one, and preſides over the Church, is moſt preſumptuouſly contemned; and the man dignified with a vocation from God, is thought unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy thereof by men.</q> That St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> writes thus, not in reference to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> but to <hi>himſelf</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Biſhops of <hi>particular</hi> Churches, is evinced by <hi>Goular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> in his Annotations, <hi>ad Epiſt.</hi> 55. <hi>n.</hi> 27. againſt <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melius.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:41190:15"/>
            <p>With great reaſon therefore did the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> decree, <hi>Can.</hi> 6. <q>
                  <hi>Antiqui mores ſerventur, &amp;c.</hi> Let the Ancient cuſtomes and priviledges be preſerved, That the Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria</hi> may have the Juniſdiction and power of them who are in <hi>Egypt, Lybia</hi> and <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tapolis;</hi> for ſo the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> hath cuſtomarily had (over his Province.) Likewiſe alſo in <hi>Antiochia</hi> and other Provinces, let their Priviledges be preſerved (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable) to their (reſpective) Churches. The <hi>Epitome</hi> of which <hi>Canon</hi> runs thus: <hi>Super Aegyptum, Lybiam, &amp; Pentapolim, Alexandrinus Epiſcopus poteſtatem habeat, &amp; Romanus ſuper Romae ſubditos. Item Antiochenus alii<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſupêr ſuos: i. e.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">V. <hi>Pandect.</hi> à <hi>Guil. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verege</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. in 1. Concil. <hi>Nice.</hi> Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 6.</note> Let the Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria</hi> have Authority over <hi>Egypt, Lybia,</hi> and <hi>Pentapolis,</hi> and the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> over the Subjects of <hi>Rome.</hi> In like manner the Biſhop of <hi>Antioch,</hi> and (all) other Biſhops over their Subjects (in their reſpective Provinces.)</q> And <hi>Alex. Ariſtenus</hi> hath this <hi>Gloſs</hi> upon it,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Unumquemque Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarcharum,</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Every Patriarch ought to be content with his own priviledges, and not to uſurp upon any other Province which was not heretofore, and from the beginning, under his power and Juriſdiction; for this is the pride of an (unjuſt) ſecular Dominion.</q> And in the <hi>Second</hi> General Council held at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> Can. 2. it is decreed thus: <q>The Biſhop ſhall not paſs the bounds of their own Dioceſſes, nor confound (the priviledges of) the Churches, but govern themſelves according to the Canons: And if we obſerve the Canon preſcribed concerning Dioceſſes, it is clear that each Province ſhall be governed by the particular Synod of the ſame Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, as it is decreed by the Council of <hi>Nice.</hi>
               </q> And <hi>Leo</hi> the Great had ſo great a veneration and zeal for the Authority and honour of that Synod, that in an Epiſtle to <hi>Anatolius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> blaming him highly amongſt other miſcarriages, for <hi>invading</hi> the priviledges
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41190:16"/>of the Churches of <hi>Alexandria</hi> and <hi>Antioch,</hi> he writes thus: <q>I grieve not a little, that you are fallen into ſo great an Error as to attempt the violation of the moſt ſacred Conſtitutions of the Canons of <hi>Nice. viz.</hi> In attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to invade, after <hi>Alexandria</hi> and <hi>Antioch,</hi> the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities and priviledges of all other <hi>Metropolitans:</hi>
               </q> And blaming him for endeavouring to <hi>wheadle</hi> the moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>Emperour,</hi> and the holy <hi>Synod</hi> (called by his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, for the extinguiſhing of Hereſie and the Confirmation of the Catholick Faith) to ſerve his ambitious deſigns, he tells him, <q>That the Synod of <hi>Nice,</hi> conſiſting of three hundred and eighteen Biſhops, was ſo <hi>Sacred,</hi> and conſecrated<note n="*" place="margin">Tanto divinitùs privilegio Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta.</note> with ſo great a priviledge from God, that whatſoever was done by any of their Councils, be they never ſo numerous, who aſſembled in them, it ſhould be utterly void and of no Authority,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Leo Mag.</hi> Epiſt. 53. inter ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra <hi>Paris,</hi> 1623.</note> if it were dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering from what was Ordained by thoſe Holy Fathers<note n="†" place="margin">Quicquid abiliorum fuerit Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutione diverſum.</note>.</q> And in his Epiſtle to <hi>Martianus</hi> the Emperour, blaming the Ambition of <hi>Anatolius,</hi> as aforeſaid, he condemns him for this reaſon; <q>
                  <hi>Privilegia enim Eccleſiarum, &amp;c.</hi> For the priviledges of the Churches being eſtabliſhed by the Canons of the Holy Fathers, and fixed by the Decrees of the venerable Synod of <hi>Nice,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Let the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider well theſe weighty Letters of his great Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors.</note> are not to be changed or ſhaken by any wicked attempts of Novelty; but to be preſerved inviolable: In which buſineſs, with Chriſts help, it is neceſſary that I exert my utmoſt endeavours as one inſtructed with a Diſpenſation. And it would become my guilt, if the Sacred Conſtitutions of the Fathers eſtabliſhed by the Holy Ghoſt in the Synod of <hi>Nice,</hi> for the Government of the whole Church of God, ſhould through my neglect or connivence<note n="‖" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lud. Bail.</hi> reads it, Te (quod abſit) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivente: and ſo applies it to the Emperour. In Sum. Concil. Tom. 1. m. p. 141. B. 2.</note> (which God forbid) be violated or infringed, and the gratifying of one Brothers humor ſhould be of more concern to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41190:16"/>me than the common benefit of the whole Church of God.</q> And in an Epiſtle to <hi>Juvenalis</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the reſt of the Biſhops aſſembled in the holy Synod of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> he writes thus concerning the keeping of the Ordinances of the holy Fathers, which are fixed by invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable Decrees in the Synod of <hi>Nice.</hi> 
               <q>I adviſe, That the rights of the Church may remain as they were ordained by thoſe three hundred and eighteen Fathers, divinely inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. Let not wicked Ambition covet anothers Right, nor let any man ſeek to augment himſelf by the leſſening of another. For by what aſſentations ſoever a vain ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may arm it ſelf, and think to ſtrengthen its inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate deſires by the name of <hi>Councils,</hi> whatſoever ſhall be diſagreeable to the Canons of the foreſaid Fathers ſhall be void and of no validity.</q> 
               <hi>Thus</hi> Leo <hi>the Great.</hi> And if there were any ſuch thing as Infallibility or Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, either in this Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the Great, or in that firſt General, and moſt ſacred Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> that Canon of theirs concerning the Juriſdiction and Priviledges of the Churches, is of full force, and ought to be obſerved in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violably at this day.</p>
            <p>Now to apply this to our own caſe. It is evident out of ſeveral Records,<note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Bedes</hi> Hiſtor. and the berty of the <hi>Brïtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick</hi> Ch. by Dr. <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier.</hi> Lond. printed for <hi>John Mileſon.</hi> 1661.</note> That the <hi>Britannick</hi> Church was ever <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and Independent, ſubject to no <hi>foreign</hi> Biſhop, but under her own <hi>Metropolitan,</hi> having her Primacy and Headſhip, with all priviledge Eccleſiaſtical, within her ſelf for ſix hundred years after Chriſt, till <hi>Auſtin</hi> the Monk, tranſgreſſing that Canon of <hi>Nice,</hi> did by <hi>force of Arms</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due and captivate her to the See of <hi>Rome.</hi> The Popes Uſurpation began here in blood, with the ſlaughter of Twelve hundred innocent and holy Monks, at <hi>Bangor;</hi> and all attempts to reinforce that Uſurpation, are carried on by methods of the like nature, <hi>i. e.</hi> practices of fraud and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>W. Beverege</hi> Anno. ad Can. 6. Concil. <hi>Nicae.</hi> p. 58, 59.</note> Nevertheleſs, as the Learned <hi>Beverege</hi> hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, the unjuſt violation of that Canon, cannot preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41190:17"/>the high and perpetual Authority of it. Wherefore though the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> ever ſince he ſent the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid <hi>Auſtin</hi> hither, hath exerciſed the chief Authority in this Nation; yet at laſt having ſhaken off his Tyrannical yoak, our Church (through Gods bleſſing) doth moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly enjoy her Ancient priviledges, by that moſt worthy Ordinance and Canon, preſcribed by the Univerſal Church, in this matter.</p>
            <p>It is manifeſt then, that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> can afford you no good <hi>Sanctuary</hi> againſt the Authority of that Biſhop and Metropolitan, whoſe Communion you have forſaken. What therefore St. <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaith againſt <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> I may fitly apply to the Pope of <hi>Rome, Tu qui regulas quaeris Eccleſiaſticas, &amp;</hi> Nicaeni <hi>Concilii Canonibus uteris, &amp; alienos Clericos &amp; cum ſuis Epiſcopis commorantes tibi niteris uſurpare; Reſponde mihi, Ad</hi> Alexandrinum <hi>Epiſcopum</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtinam <hi>quid pertinet.</hi> Thou who ſeekeſt for Eccleſiaſtical Canons, and uſeſt the Conſtitutions of the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> and notwithſtanding pretendeſt to uſurp the Government over the Clergy of other Biſhops, tell me, what hath the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> to do with Great <hi>Britain?</hi> Sir, from what hath been ſuggeſted it is evident, that the Biſhop and Church of <hi>Rome</hi> have ſhamefully prevaricated both the Doctrine and Government of the Catholick Church, as it was declared and fix'd by the moſt Ancient and ſacred Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Councils; The Doctrine, as well in matters of Faith as Manners; And the Government by uſurping the Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction and priviledges of other Churches.</p>
            <p>And if (as you profeſs) you have not changed your Loyalty, I am very apt to believe, the wicked Plot now under Examination (with many of the like nature) may be ſufficient to make you abhor the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of that Church, whoſe Morals can hatch ſuch Monſters, and whoſe Governours do make it their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to Lowbel their pliant Creatures into deſigns of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41190:17"/>Treaſon and Aſſaſſination, by the help of falſe Lights, Bulls and Diſpenſations; and encourage them in the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts by the fond applauſe of Merit, and a Crown of <hi>Red Letters.</hi> In ſhort, the ſcandal hereof is ſo foul, it may very well become your ingenuity (and without doubt it will tend much to your reputation and inward peace) to take your leave of ſuch Company, with good old <hi>Jacobs</hi> imprecation, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.6. <hi>O my Soul, come not thou into their ſecret: unto their aſſembly, my Honour, be not thou united.</hi> And this is the Advice, which proceeds (though but from the common prudence, yet) from the higheſt Charity of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt affectionate Friend, and faithful Servant, <hi>L. W.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
